good evening everyone we're gonna get started in just a few minutes there are some additional chairs along the back row which you are welcome to set up but I would just ask that you keep a center aisle clear and enough room on either side that there is safety grass in the room thank you and also with that being said there are some additional seats I'm seeing up here and if you have an empty seat next to you wave your hand so everyone has a place to sit if they wish good evening everyone it is a bit after 630 so we are going to get started again there should be some extra chairs stacked along the back if you wish to have a seat during the meeting we just ask that you keep aisles clear for safe safe egress in the room now call to order this meeting of Lancaster City Council for March 11th 2025 a few reminders at the top of the meeting for everyone please take a moment to silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already this meeting and its participants are being recorded and live-streamed anyone addressing council during public comment period should please do so at the podium in order to be heard in the room and on the livestream please begin all comments with your name and block of residence for our meeting record public comment is limited to three minutes per speaker I will be using this light in front of me to keep time it will turn green when three minutes begins it will turn yellow when there is one minute remaining and will turn red when three minutes has been exhausted and i want to thank everyone in advance for ensuring that everyone has an equal time also just a meeting a meeting note the women's history month resolution that was slated for this evening has been postponed until our next regular meeting and now for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the pledge of
allegiance i pledge allegiance mr harris would you please call the role of members yes madam president
mr. met here mr. Arroyo here mr. police yeah miss Craig misty is here mr. Hirsch
here president Baker here councillor Craig is excused this evening we will now move to the approval of the minutes of the February 25th 2025 meeting most into a proof second we have a motion and a second any council comments on the meeting minutes hearing none mr. Harris mr. Mudd aye mr. royal aye mr. Cleese
aye miss Diaz aye mr. Hirsch aye president Baker aye next item is
proclamations honors and awards and resolutions of recognition again as I noted at the top of the meeting the Women's History Month resolution is postponed until our next regular meeting that will take us to our first public comment period reserved for residents who contacted the city clerk prior to the meeting to request to speak in this period again comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and must begin with your name and block of residence before we go into public comment we have several and I know that the there is a topic that I believe everyone is here for I want to just make a quick statement I would like to ensure members of the public that the use of use of force review for the March 2nd incident is underway currently the review will involve a thorough examination of all body cameras and other footage that is available. Members of Council and the public will be updated on the findings when the review is completed. While I understand that the video posted online is a small part of an interaction, I agree personally that what I saw was disturbing and I look forward to hearing the outcome of the review and from Chief Mendez during a more formal report to Council from a public safety that has been requested by councillor Ahmed that will occur at an upcoming meeting mr. Harris if we could begin with public comment please yes madam president first
this evening is alaya mochios is alaya here next is grace Musser his grace
Musser in the room we can recall these names at the end next mr. Harris
andrea hirsch adriana good evening good evening uh good evening council in my capacity as the former executive director of the commonweal i got to know the youth on bikes who we affectionately referred to as the wheelie kids and like many teens their age it took a lot of time and effort to get to know them and more importantly earn their trust teens are by no means perfect i should know i was once a teen we know their frontal lobes are not developed until 25 years of age and that they will make mistakes sometimes the same ones time after time however this does not warrant police to use force against them when i worked with the wheelie kids i would encourage safe behavior when i witnessed law breaking i instructed my staff to withhold the services they sought out weekly because your actions do have consequences perhaps our police could call parents and impound bicycles without resorting to force still imparting lessons while doing less harm further still i'd encourage police to use part of their community engagement budget which they did not fully spend in 2024 to buy bike lights to give to kids i think working to build trust with them through positive engagement would go a long way for them to follow the law i would also encourage our police to get out of their vehicles which by nature insulate all of us from the world around us police used to be beat cops getting to know neighborhoods and neighbors now they drive through our city waiting to be called to a crime we need to know and trust our police not to have them behind the closed doors of a police suv many people think wheelie kids are a menace but their bikes give them purpose they practice tricks day and night meanwhile i can barely let go of one handlebar to signal and i've been told bikes keep them out of gangs perhaps with more emotional intelligence training our police can approach our teens from a place of understanding and compassion thank you mr harris our next speaker yes president next is nick
silvery hiller good evening evening uh nick silvery hiller 400 block or 500 block of north Plum Street. I'm not going to hide my frustration and anger right now because I've been living in this city for ten years and over those ten years I've seen the police repeatedly brutalize black and brown youth in this city. When I first moved here a couple years after I first moved here we all saw the video of a man sitting on with his hands behind his back on the sidewalk get tased in the back while following orders that was my one my earliest introductions to Lancaster and repeatedly in 2020 I know I've talked to you all a lot in here during 2020 I saw police officers brutalize youth in the streets protesting for their rights including pepper spraying folks at point-blank range and I got some of that pepper spray because of the wind myself so I've seen repeatedly repeatedly this brutality that our police officers do to our communities and it frustrates me because we see how open the city is to rich tourists and not our own neighbors I am one of the I'm a member and organizer with the party for socialism and liberation and I'm one of the co-signers of I'm sure the statement that you've all seen and I just would like to reiterate those statements and I hope other signers will reiterate them and others will repeat them one the demand is to reinstate the Civilian Review Board, formerly known as a community police working group that was dismantled with no reason announced to the public. Two, we call for the firing of Officer Hatfield and the names of the unidentified officers from Chief Mendez's police department present at the scene to be released. And three, for the police to uphold accountability and transparency with the community by releasing the body camera footage to the public. Many of you have put out statements calling for accountability and transparency in vague terms. These are just three of the first steps that you can take to actually demonstrate that transparency and accountability that you're boasting that you support. Thank you.
Mr. Harris.
Yes, next is Jessica Lopez.
Good evening.
My name is Jessica Lopez. I'm a Lancaster City resident. I refuse to give my address out of safety concerns. I'm sure you guys understand. I'm going to start with the next part. i appreciate counselor med i appreciate counselor world i appreciate you mr colleagues there i appreciate you miss bakey and i do appreciate you mr i'm going to start with the nice part your guys's statements were on the money i appreciate you using your voice and advocating in that faction do i believe that city council could possibly do a little bit more to push the education of these kids for these kids every year yes they could because every year we have new kids that get to ride bikes because they get old enough to ride bikes every year those kids grow they don't get handed the bicycle crime code those kids get they get helmets they get knee pads they get sat on their bikes they learn how to ride those bikes and nobody tells them what the laws are me as a mother before this situation transpired I didn't know what the bike laws were how do you expect every mother in this city to work hard to pay taxes and then know all your bike crime codes now with that being said it takes a village to raise a child and our elected officials to hold those put in place to protect them accountable chief mendez's police department and his absent present in the community he grew up in and his failure to control his officers has shown the black and brown community that they afford us no protections and that we should fear interactions with them i do not let my children go outside what should have been a teaching moment by officers to these kids turned into a traumatic life-altering event those kids will never look at their bikes or any cop in the same way ever again. The statement that the police department released today is not only slandering these children, because prove it. Prove that each and every one of those kids that were assaulted committed those acts that still don't deserve that response none of those things on that list says put your hands on me if those children are not an immediate danger to our community or to ourselves and that doesn't mean bumping into somebody with their bike there's no reason why those grown men with guns put their hands on them so the police department's response over my three minutes give me just give me just because i got to get this out the police department's response to what to what to defend an officer who stood by while his fellow officer punched a man in the face in 2015 he didn't protect that man to what protect the man who was listed with ryan yoder in a civil rights claim in 2023 to protect him who listed two months ago in another civil rights lawsuit this is all public information online because what yous are protecting them more than you're protecting us at what point do you cage your dogs the city of lancaster is known for its gross misconduct issues and you've continually passed the buck instead of taking responsibility in action and janet diaz's statement is a prime example of the out of touch advocacy and gaslighting that transpires in this community pray you never become our mayor the the mayor's the exiting mayor's silence on this situation proves she never belongs here we are no longer accepting the status quo and the complacency that transpires among those who we put on a pedestal is long gone we're tired of being used and accepting abuse disregarded and manipulated we are not here for you to look good we are not here for use we put y'all in place for us to protect our kids and our community and with that i will walk away and i like i said i thank those who chose to use their platform to advocate for these kids but at this point more needs to be done i shouldn't be getting these videos on sunday night and spending nine days organizing this this is wrong i do not get paid by the city and i'm tired of being re-traumatized every day that i open my phone up it's not fair and if you want me to shut up do your jobs thank you mrs our next speaker
Next speaker is Darlene Byrd.
Ms. Byrd, good evening.
Hi, Darlene Byrd. First I want to talk about two other issues before we address the police issue. Two council meetings ago I was here and I requested a report about how many people got tickets on the day that it snowed when our trash set out three weeks. I have not heard from any council person about that report or the number. I know it's very high. It's in the southeast area i'm here again to request that report i have an email for you i just got this afternoon okay thank you also i'm here to i addressed the issue about the uh a report on how many accidents was on um east end avenue on franklin street that they got a stop sign put there when we have been requesting since 2017 that a stop sign be placed on green and ann street which is a very dangerous intersection we have many members from the community come to this meeting and many traffic meetings and we're not heard and we're no longer going to say we're not going to be heard we want are we talking about safety now with the police we requested a citizens review board so many years ago it is time that we get a citizens review board to bring trust and communication into the
community thank you yes I'm going to come up and use guys this proposed
resolution and along with that I'm also going to hand you the city of Lancaster's commitment to racial equity that came out in 2020 that has not been put in place and we feel is not being followed. Good evening my name is Jessica Lopez and I'm here today speaking on behalf of John Mena. He and I are proudly representing The Collective, a coalition following Lancaster organizations, the Black Voter Outreach Network of PA, the Democratic Socialists of America, the Lancaster Bail Fund, the Lancaster Changemakers Collective. Lancaster stands up and the party for socialism and liberation tonight we are submitting a document for public record that outlines concerns regarding the Lancaster City Police Department's recent interactions with black and Latino residents specifically this document highlights the March 2nd 2025 incident involving the use of force against several Latino teens as well as other recent cases that have raised serious concerns about transparency and accountability within the department. We recognize that Chief Mendez is a lifelong Lancaster resident and a veteran officer in this city. Given his deep ties to the community, we believe it is reasonable to expect leadership that actively works to improve trust between law enforcement and the public, particularly for marginalized communities. However, the continued use of force and lack of these escalation involving black and Latino residences raised significant questions. What steps are being taken to prevent incidences like this from happening again how does the police department ensure officers follow de-escalation policies before resorting to force why our previous uses of force reports unavailable to the public repeat why our previous use of force reports unavailable to the public and when will they be made accessible and I guess this would go for Janet but what does your Public Safety Committee committee do? Do they work with the police directly? Are we letting them lead this? Our request tonight is straightforward. We urge the city council to consider passing a reasonable resolution calling for an immediate, transparent, and independent review of this latest incident and public available findings. Additionally, we ask to create a formal public safety commission or authority that includes council and community members and provides oversight on policing policies along with the commission we asked for a community partnership including a civilian review board these are measures necessary first steps to establish trust between law enforcement in the communities where they serve our collective formally acknowledges the lancaster city police department statement on the incident on 3 10 25 they released a vague statement that left that left us with more concerns than answers this response is unacceptable and not enough An unsigned statement informing the public of internal investigation is not reasonable, transparent, or acceptable for behavior that is a pattern. The decisions made in response to this issue will send a clear message about Lancaster City's commitment to public safety, accountability, and justice. There are opportunities here to take the first step in building trust with the community. We look forward to working collaboratively to ensure all residents feel protected, respected, and heard. Please accept this resolution on request on our behalf. We look forward to your responses. Thank you very much. And that was John Maynard, not Jessica.
No justice, no peace.
No peace.
Mrs. Harris, our next speaker.
Our next speaker is Daryl Lagace.
Good evening.
Evening. My name is Daryl Lagacy. I live in the 100 block of North Mary. Thank you for allowing me to address the council. here to talk about the interaction that happened that we're probably all here for people say that you don't know what happened before the video started they say the kids were doing wheelies they were going the wrong way down the street maybe yeah maybe they were it doesn't justify having someone two to three times the weight of that kid with his knee on his back face down not resisting crying for help like that just when you look at that I don't know how you can see that and say oh yeah that's the right response I hear a lot of people complain about cancel culture they say they're afraid to be cancelled for saying the wrong thing or doing the wrong thing when I don't see our police worried about being cancelled I don't see police officers worried about what it looks like when they kneel on someone saying they can't breathe we've done this for five years really for a hundred years and I don't see them being worried when they push someone who's recording them which happened twice in that video it's unacceptable so I'm calling for four things one release the names of all police officers involved in that situation release all the body cam footage leading up to and during the encounter reinstate the community police working group and require de-escalation training for all officers to everyone here and everyone in the city i'm asking you to record every single public police encounter from now on especially those with people of color i realize i'm a white person i am privileged i mostly don't have to worry about this i don't want to be here speaking tonight but I feel like I have to be it's your constitutional right to record police if it is in public so here people say oh you complain about the police and then you're the first one to go running to them when you need something yeah that's the job okay that's their job no one made them become police officers no one said they had to do this if this is too hard or if they're not happy they can quit. They work for us, not the other way around.
Our next speaker is our next speaker.
Our next speaker is Megan Keller.
Is Megan here with us tonight? I'll recall the beginning and the end. Our next speaker,
Mr. Harris. Our next speaker is Jontel Toland.
Good evening. I'm Jontel Toland, first and only block of Wise Ave. I recently saw a video that disturbed me. A toddler held at gunpoint by police was lying on the ground beside her mother both belly down forced into submission so imagine being a child barely old enough to form full sentences having to stay perfectly still so you aren't killed by a trigger-happy officer the footage from March 2nd is equally disturbing what we saw was not just an overreach it was intimidation abuse of power and a blatant disregard for the rights of our youth minors stopped for lacking bike reflectors at 630 p.m. it's hardly a justification for detention and yet they were treated like criminals the law is clear minors cannot be questioned without a parent present but instead of protection these children were met with force one even pinned down to the ground in an officer kneeling on his back imagine being that teenager doing your best to remain calm while being terrified and why shouldn't they be afraid in a country where a 12 year old boy was gunned down for playing a toy gun fear is rational thank god some of these kids knew their rights thank god one of them filled the interaction because without that recording we might not be having this conversation i know fear personally and And as a child, too, I was abused by police. I, too, have felt the weight of an officer's force. And I know that trauma doesn't end when the moment is over. It lingers, leaving scars that can take years and even a lifetime to heal. Seeing the events on March 2 chills me to my bone, because I know what happens when power goes unchecked. Who is the enemy here? The children riding their bikes, or a system that continues to terrorize the most vulnerable among us? Lancaster is a city of contrast, and there is so much beauty here, yet we continue to make headlines for excessive force and police misconduct. Our history hasn't been kind to people of color, to the poor, to the unhoused, or anyone deemed marginalized. And in these moments, history repeats itself. There is a clear disconnect between some officers and the communities they are meant to serve. We cannot afford to have police officers patrolling neighborhoods they do not understand or respect. Community policing, true community policing, is about relationships, trust, guidance, and not intimidation. A missing bike reflector should be a teachable moment, not an excuse for aggression. I understand that officers are human, but a bad day for them should not become a lifelong trauma for someone else. The people of Lancaster, most importantly our children, deserve better. They deserve to play, to exercise, to simply exist without the looming threat of police brutality. If we claim to be a just city, we must act like one. And that starts with accountability. That starts with asking why this officer is still in the force and what we should do to rectify this situation. So I also echo the coalition of local orgs who have issued the statement with the demands of reinstating the Civilian Review Board, firing Officer Hatfield, releasing body camera footage. And I ask you to think about community, think about your own children, and think about creating better dialogue with our community about how we treat one another. Thank you.
Our next speaker is Amber Farmer.
Hi, my name's Amber Farward from the 700 block of Fifth Street. I am a citizen of this city. I've been my entire adult life. And I am currently missing my son's first soccer practice to be here to do all this with you guys. Because I am a mother, this is very important to me. I want my son. I see my son and that child in that video. And I want a safe place for him to run around with his friends and have fun and ride his bike without fear. I don't feel that right now in this city. And my other point that I wanted to make is that I'm a licensed professional counselor. I've dedicated my career to working with children and advocating for them and keeping them safe. If I ever was told or saw a video of one of my clients being kneeled on by an adult, I would have to contact Child Protective Services. And I couldn't in good conscience not show up here today and ask that you all keep our children safe.
Mandatory. Thank you. Next speaker.
Next speaker is David Miller Glick.
Good evening. Good evening. My name is David Miller Glick, and I live on Haker Street in Lancaster City. I'm a volunteer organizer with Lancaster Stands Up. And I stand before you today as a concerned citizen and a father who is both fearful and angry. I'm angry because Officer Hatfield and all other officers who were present during the March 2 incident failed to act like adults, much less officers of the law. There is no excuse for a routine traffic stop to escalate to the point where grown men are forcing a 15- and 16-year-old to the ground with knees on their backs. It is proof of a deep moral failure on the part of the police officers involved, as well as systemic issues that will only get worse if ignored. I am disappointed by the police department's statement, which listed minor infractions, such as trespassing in garages and pulling fire alarms, which was a lazy attempt to paint these boys as dangerous criminals. I would like to ask everyone in this room, who seems more dangerous, a few rowdy teenagers or the grown adults who violently pinned them to the pavement and made them fear for their lives? What we need is accountability, not excuses. My son is nine years old. His skin is brown. He loves to ride his bike with me. I am here today because I hope he will never be a victim of the brutality like we saw on the March 2 incident. he deserves to be able to ride his bike through the city without fear of arbitrary violence from police officers who have no business wearing the badge i demand accountability i agree with all of the statement all of the asks from the statement of re-establishing the citizen review board and releasing the body cam footage but especially officer fat hatfield needs to be fired we need to show that his bait that his behavior was unacceptable even one bad apple can
spoil the bunch thank you good evening Susie Gomez 100 block of North Reservoir Street pushing an ungodly agenda while swearing an oath to protect the people is being rebuked today you look down on us by your ignorance and can't believe that the S&P 500 is based on the standard and poor. You see things through the eyes of the wicked who pursue their agenda to kill, steal, and destroy. There is no unity in this administration because us as taxpayers who have expressed ourselves on this podium gets ignored, delayed, or denied. Let's talk, you say. Set up an appointment, you say. But public comments are suggestions, concerns etc we work to and pay you to do your job Lancaster City has lost its customs heritage foundation its name Lancaster and so Lancaster has become the home of survival to divide and conquer has always been the quest and you prey on the innocent hard workers because you are too busy closing down departments relying on IT social technology with troubleshooting interruptions, the government creates funding for all cities and states and the workers write the grants, push the intake coordinators to execute the applications to fulfill the needs of the people while they pay their taxes to be the Commonwealth that we both invest in. This is not a one-way street. Your ignorance has taught a generation to measure their work on takeaways as city contracts are being run by outsiders, permitters are forced to use benchmark, investors are catching tax breaks, and shareholders seem to be the only ones receiving equitable gain. For centuries the city relied on volunteers, interns graduates and neighborhoods to find an even balance and take care of our public officers while taking pride in the building of infrastructures cleaning of parks working together as one so that the baton can be passed to the next graduate who takes pride in the city engagements but this administration has us continuously asking for loans passing on properties to the highest bidder while handing investors lead abatement condemned properties that can be remedied by community programs such as critical repair government funding grants to help in crisis for homelessness lack of housing revitalization and more looking at you instead it's better to 80% for a new turf at a baseball field than helping a taxpayer or a non-profit struggling to maintain their business. Churches are a non-profit, but you'd rather open up new non-profits. Shame on you. Last thing, I'm sorry. We are supposed to be a common wealth, common interest. You will go down as the worst administration in Lancaster PA who killed the American dream and broke all the rules.
Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker for this comment period. Next speaker is
Amanda Reitz.
Amanda, we'll recall names at the end. Next speaker then, Mr. Harris.
Marshall Miller.
Good evening. Good evening, Marshall Miller, 100th block of East Vine Street. Thank you all for your time. I'm here to stand with my neighbors and say that the recent violent incidents involving Lancaster City Police and local teenagers were deeply disturbing and unacceptable. This and other recent videos of violent police interactions were alarming to me, and I believe they undermine the community trust in Lancaster City's police. Our police work for us. As city residents, we pay their salaries, and we have the right to demand the highest quality of service from them. I recognize that our police officers have a difficult and important job to do, and I'm thankful for the countless times they do that well, but part of their work involves accountability when we witness what appears to be a clear failure to protect our kids. These violent incidents have broken trust, and city leaders owe residents a thorough, transparent investigation into each one. I believe these recent incidents require more than a regular review they require robust more transparent investigations than your typical use of force reviews our police department owes this to residents in order to reestablish trust and I hope that you all will help us get that done moving forward what I would like to see from this chamber and city leaders is a renewed effort to recruit officers from within the city when someone lives on your block they are far less likely to put their knee on your kids back for riding a bike on the sidewalk when our officers live among us they can know residents personally give them a call when they see their kids in trouble or getting into trouble that is the power of community policing and we have to build that and I'd like to make a practical suggestion on that front currently in the city's officer recruitment process preference points are added to applicants test scores to help boost certain applicants based on their background and experience for example veterans are given 10 preference points on top of their cumulative test scores according to state law no other preference points can exceed this amount but it is my understanding that we can tweak other preference points below this amount based on other criteria currently in our police officer application process three preference points are given to candidates who live within the city's limits for two years prior to their test date also three preference points are given to candidates who can communicate in a second language I would like you all to help increase these amounts to help increase the number of successful candidates who live in the city I think a good place to start would be at least to double the current preference points for city residents so that would be six preference points for candidates who lived within the city for at least two years and I suggest we also increase the preference points for candidates who can communicate in a second language this should help build a police force that looks and lives it looks like us and lives in this communities that they serve which ultimately makes them more accountable to us the residents who pay their salaries thank you for your time and service I look forward to seeing how you take real action to change the status quo hi my name is Ann Torres I
live in Lititz I'm here this evening with a statement on behalf of the Lancaster Democratic Socialists of America the incident that occurred on March 2nd in Lancaster City between the Lancaster City police and the miners riding their bikes was reprehensible we as an organization with members who live and work in the city demand action and accountability police officers cannot be allowed to act with impunity. They cannot be allowed to forgo city policy and use force before de-escalation. And there is no reason why an interaction with children riding their bikes should end with high-level force and arrest. Is it policy for the Lancaster police to violently arrest children who don't have reflectors on their bikes? We hear the concerns of the people that say, well, what happened before the camera started rolling? And to that we ask in return, when is it okay for children to be the victim of excessive use of force? Where is the line drawn? We see time and time again in this is of police violence including in our own city when will it end what is the final straw before people stand up and say enough and demand more from those sworn to protect us if we allow officers involved in this police department and at large to be free from punishment what is next and if this is what we see when they are being recorded what is happening when no one is looking it's about this incident from members on this council and to the police Department talk of transparency and accountability. A good first start of this would be the following. One, a reinstatement of the Civilian Review Board, formerly known as the Community Police Working Group. Two, the termination of Officer Hatfield and the names of the unidentified police officers from the scene who work for Chief Mendez's Police Department to be released. Three, for the city to uphold accountability and transparency with the community by releasing the body cam footage to the public. Additionally, Lancaster DSA demands that any review of the conduct that happened on March 2nd to be evaluated by an independent third-party reviewer. The police cannot be trusted to evaluate and investigate themselves. An independent third-party investigation will allow for an unbiased review free from conflict of interest. The police officers in this city will continue to feel emboldened and increase their use of force with impunity if there are no consequences for their actions. If this is allowed to happen we will remember this moment and who ignored their community's call to action so please do not let us down help us take action now mr harris our next speaker next speaker is
good evening my name is michelle batt i am the president of the lancaster bail fund but i am not here today in my capacity as that uh president jessica lopez spoke well enough for our organization and for herself I am here as an attorney I am specifically I had the privilege of serving our indigent criminal defendant population for a number of years I have practiced criminal defense for close to a decade now and I am deeply disturbed by what I have been seeing recently not just the March 2nd incident but pepper spraying of children taking a black woman to the ground my practice I have gotten good results for my clients due to police brutality in the city Lancaster City police officer police brutality now I want to make something clear I resigned from my position as senior assistant public defender in April of 2021 so what I am talking about goes back years and I would I'm also here in my capacity as a Lancaster City resident I pay taxes and this is my most recent tax bill my property taxes are 41% of the city's revenue and the police bureau is 37 percent of the general fund expense what are the police doing with our money to ensure community safety a principle called proportionality but people laymen non-lawyers we might call it common sense how does it make sense that armed men with a monopoly on violence would be enforcing a Lancaster County City ordinance that's punishable by a maximum of $50 fine make it make sense and exactly and this ordinance indicates that lights and reflectors be on bicycles half an hour after sunset all the way through half an hour after sunrise the next day do y'all know sitting here when Sun set on March 2nd I don't even think even on the flimsiest flimsiest ground that the police have nothing to stand on here they this is straight-up bullying and I do not thank you I'm about to wrap up thank you very much but as a taxpayer I do not want my money to be spent on these armed men bullying black and brown children I have worked with black and brown children three years I have worked with black and brown children and they are fucking gems okay so I want to ask a couple things one please please consider the proposed resolution that has been introduced tonight please please consider putting officer Hatfield on desk duty please please acknowledge what has happened because a failure to acknowledge what has happened a repetition of the bullshit excuse that the police put out on WD AL earlier is only going to serve to divide this community further what we need is accountability and it wouldn't hurt if you paid for these children's therapy
is iris here our next speaker mr harris jacqueline william william good evening hello
my name is jacqueline william i am a resident of the 100 block of east clay street and i'm here tonight because i'm a member of the cycling community and i'd like to speak about the recent events where the city has made the streets unsafe for everyone on march 2nd some young people on bikes were stopped by the lancaster city police bureau these boys did not experience safe streets despite the ongoing work by the city instead they experienced quite the opposite when they were harassed and assaulted by police officers over not having front lights a city police officer placed his knee on a kid's back over this a city police officer shoved and harassed a woman passing by for filming their actions a city police officer maced one of these boys there have been some public incidences of lancaster city police harassing cyclists in the past all while simultaneously breaking laws themselves regarding safe passing has escalated like the incident on march 2nd and this incident only escalated because these kids weren't white as has been mentioned earlier the penalty for not having a front light after sunset is a fine of not more than fifty dollars there is no way to justify the actions that occurred on march 2nd no matter what happened before the video started i am requesting that the city terminate the employment of all of the officers involved in this incident these officers have proven that given the opportunity they will harm people and one bad apple spoils the entire barrel i would also like to request that following these officers terminations the city reinstate a civilian review board people who like to hurt people and exert power over others are a poison to our entire community and they need to be removed
from positions of power mr harris if my notes are correct that was our final pre-registered public comment for this evening that's correct thank you uh i will remind you folks we do have a second comment period at the end of the meeting for issues that weren't on the agenda which you're welcome to stay for we do have our uh legislative agenda before us this evening but if you are wishing to leave at this time you can do so we will move on with the meeting and i want to thank everyone for their comments this evening we do also we do also have a council comments further on in the agenda so as we will continue with the agenda our next item is report requested by council mrs. Harris confirming that we don't have any of those on the agenda this evening is that correct thank you all right we will then move to reports of committees of council meetings which were held on March 3rd 2025 our first is public safety councillor Diaz is not in the room at the moment so we'll forgo her report the next is public works committee councillor Hershey report
thank you council president the public works committee did meet on our committee excuse me March 3rd there was no legislative action taken or considered but we did hear a report from the Department of Public Works on the city's revamped trees for people program they gave us a lot of exciting updates about things coming this year including the planning of 376 street trees and you can learn more sorry at cityoflakes.ca.gov slash services slash trees and that That concludes the Public Works Committee report.
Thank you very much, Councilor Hirsch. Economic Development Committee, Councilor Mett.
Thank you, Council President. The Economic Development Committee did not meet in our office.
Thank you. Councilor Roy, Finance Committee.
Thank you, Council President. The Finance Committee did meet. We discussed Administration Bill number 1, 2025, which does appear later in the agenda for its first reading. That concludes our report, Council President.
Thank you. I will also turn to you for Community Planning Committee in the absence of Councilor Craig.
Yes, thank you. Community Planning Committee did meet during the last session. We'll discuss two resolutions, resolution number 19-2025, excuse me, 20-2025, and resolution number 22-2025, which also appears later in the agenda. That concludes my report.
Thank you. We're turning to public safety. It's your back, Councilor Diaz.
Yes, we had met, and we spoke on resolution 80-2025, 2025 which would be removing all the older records and disposing them and I would bring that up on our next agenda legislation. Thank you. And Personnel Committee, Councilor Cleese.
Thank you Madam President. The Personnel Committee did meet on March 3rd and we view a nomination for appointment to the City Revitalization and Improvement District and a reappointment to the Board of Health. That concludes my report, Madam President.
Thank you very much. We will now move into our legislative agenda where the first item are nominations for appointments. Counselor, please.
Thank you, Madam President. Those nominations were reviewed on March 3rd. There isn't anything to add, so I'll make a motion to appoint Stephen Grosh to the City Revitalization and Improvement Zone of O'Reilly for a term from december 31st 2024 to december 31st 2029 and we appointed jessica emmy to the board of health for a term from march 31st 2025 to march 31st 2013. thank you we have a motion
and a second on the appointments any council comments on those comments from the public on
on the appointments good evening good evening my comment is on the member that people are rejecting council the member that the gentleman that came in from another city to be on the board of the revitalization board he does not have experience nor did he go to any type of training in the city of Lancaster to know um like when we get graduates uh and we go into act 101 or certain different members um associations to be on the board there's steps that need to be followed with lancaster city alliance and we feel that an outsider should not hold that position so we reject the gentleman that's coming in from another city who clearly stated in our last meeting that he has no experience i speak on behalf of the people maybe not you so and you're his wife that's that's fine that's his wife uh revitalization board that's your wife that's
talking thank you for coaching the room the chris board has several members a number of them are city residents required some of them are open to other members in lancaster community including business owners and this particular gentleman who came to our meeting on the third was an appointee from senator scott martin's office which he has a seat on this board to fill i believe he just has the one seat on this board so we have the majority of seats to fill this was a senator martin appointment that was brought before us on the third any additional comments from the public on
this one on the appointments and who senator martin is to do that thank you andre brock of
coral street now gave him the decision to do this this is written into the bylaws of the
chris board so you guys are going to hire from other cities to come here and what to do or how
to do our neighborhood volunteer position this is not a hire but still we we got alumni from
mccaskey that could do that my grandson is in college right now he could do that you go and
get people from outside to do that thank you and i apologize it's not about it's a state law i need additional comments from the public on appointments before us
Tony D'Astra, 700 block New Holland Avenue. Just for the sake of education and for future appointments, what are the amount of positions and who can appoint them for the CRIZ authority board? how many are city exclusive how might how many might be elected officials and um i guess a follow-up question to any of that is any nominations made by elected officials or other entities um is the city allowed to request an alternative nomination be put forward uh that's
all i got thank you thank you mr dastra uh i don't believe we are able to uh ask for an alternative nomination unless there's more than one that would come up for us in this case there there was not there's nine members and there are two non-voting members which do represent Senator Scott Martin's office by state law and also city staff again there are non-voting members so the nine members again one is an appointment from Senator Martin's office any additional comments from the public
on the appointments Darlene Byrd Ann Street I think this is an opportunity for for council to help and educate the voters and the public. We come before council with nominations for many of our commissions and our authorities. There is very little information out there on what the responsibilities, what's the requirement. I feel there is a lack of reaching out, especially to the black and brown community, to sit on these authorities and these boards or to get more local people. Council needs to figure a way out with our technology how to educate the public about these, so when nominations are made and come up here, the information that we got today should have been out there, so we should know. So I'm just asking that council would take the time to educate people about the commissions and authorities, how long they're serving, why they're serving 10 years, why they're serving five years, and let us know. Thank you.
Any further comments from the public on the appointments before us?
As a member of the personnel committee, I do want to state that Mr. Grosh did come before the committee at the Monday meeting. Mr. Grosh was appointed by Senator Scott Martin. He has been practicing law in the city for many years. Senator Scott Martin's office believed that he would bring a unique perspective. We did question Mr. Grosh on how he plans to use CRIPS to promote equitable economic development in the city. and we felt comfortable with his answers as a person thank you any additional
comments on the next item on the agenda are items for the historic district mr. Harris if you
when you're ready
we have a motion and a second thank you just one additional note that the Harb
found that the change in the storefront window was an appropriate modern alteration for the use that was approved by the zoning hearing board and they
unanimously recommended this approval thank you any additional comments on the recommendation from the public hearing none mr harris next item on the agenda these are ordinance this is an ordinance for first reading again there's no action being taken on this Wednesday it's administration bill number one 2025 mr harris
an ordinance authorizing the occurrence of non-electoral debt of the city of lancaster lancaster county pennsylvania by the issuance of principal amount of general obligation bonds series of 2025 issued for the purpose of providing funds for one general municipal projects including upgrades and improvements cities wastewater collection and treatment facilities the city's water treatment and distribution facilities the city's parks and related facilities the streets and traffic signals within the city and related facilities each set forth on exhibit a attached here to and other capital projects of the city as determined by the city two capitalizing interest on the bonds and three paying the cost of issuing and ensuring the bonds determined to sell the series of 2025 bonds the 2025 bonds at a private sale play invitation approving the form of the series of the 2025 bonds fixing the number of date interest and maturities in the 2025 bonds making a covenant for the payment of the debt service of the 2025 bonds pledging the full faith credit and taxing power of this city in support of such bonds providing for the filing of required documents providing for the appointment of a sinking fund depository for the 2025 bonds and authorizing execution sale and delivery thereof and other necessary action thank you
mr harris it's a lengthy title i appreciate that uh counselor do you have anything to add at this
time uh nothing much to add just that the expected uh total amount of the bonds is expected to be 38.4 million dollars um for projects that should be completed within the next three years
thank you i'll make a note this was in my notes from the um from the committee meeting that the indebtedness was a part of our 10-year projections that council was provided with over the course of the last year plus so this isn't new in planning this is just simply actually taking out the bonds that were projected to be done is that correct to your notes thank you any additional council comments again this is a first reading tonight so there's no action being taken from the public
johnny dastro 700 block new holland avenue uh i only have a question uh as it relates to trash billing actually because um you know i think this gets a little weird and complicated for me because utilities are supposed to generate enough revenue to service themselves definitely recognize that when your utilities need work you got to finance the project somehow otherwise you're drinking crap water so i'm not knocking that but i would like to know what the status is of the most recent um i don't know if we've requested the puc change our rates for out of city trash billing customers so i just would like to know the status of that since it kind of relates
to financing of these sort of projects yeah sewer sorry yeah I don't know why I was saying trash yes so the the water rate has already started the sewer rate
will start once the water rate is complete later this year thank you any
additional comments on this one for first reading tonight again no actions
being taken this evening good evening good evening Susie Gomez this presentation that was done a week ago on this bond Lancaster City is paying for contaminated water that's number one you got funding from nine million to seven million to fix pipes lead all this stuff and you still want to attack the homeowners and the residents to change their lead pipes what are you going to do in terms of offering them some type of solution rather than be like my father where the city came in and said we need to go in to replace these pipes we have to see if you have lead pipes and then told him oh yeah you need to replace this and then my father said well how much is it going to cost it was close to $5,000 and when he came here to the city and shared with the individual who's in charge of this that he wasn't able to pay they wanted to condemn the property that he lives in you guys need to be a little bit more accountable for everything and it's unfair now the bond the guy mentioned borrowing to save more tomorrow this is a long-term borrowing process that's going to take 25 years of taxpayers money that we're gonna have to repay I don't think Tina Campbell did a great job in introducing this to the public because many of us are still confused okay we have the right to know details and we have the right to hold you accountable in any proceedings that
has in this city especially neighborhood engagement so I say that because there's
not enough information that is being given to the taxpayers in Lancaster City about decisions that you guys are making that we have to follow protocol I need
everybody in the room to please come to order we will have decorum during the meeting Ms. Gomez please continue your comments this does not go against your time
the debt is 391 million dollars and I'm not saying that this occurred in the last two years I'm saying that this occurred in the last seven years the water issue that we have in the plant was known 30 years ago we are sitting on our last 10 years as to whether or not you guys raised enough money to change that water system that is decades if not centuries old and we have to stand here and watch increases in our utility bills but you guys don't have no remedy it is shameful okay there's a woman on Fremont Street who took a shower and her skin was literally peeling and you guys went in and replaced her pipes and then sent her a letter we have lead in our water we know these things what is the solution to tax us more money to make it more harder for the average American citizen for the taxpayers in Lancaster City to provide food on their table for their children you guys don't have no solutions you keep hiring outsiders to conduct business in our city that don't
no shit about Lancaster the detail is the projects were included with the bill and are posted and publicly available they do include infrastructure improvements for that line replacement and transit aging pipe replacement so this is in part paying for the infrastructure that is long overdue and has been long deferred in the city of Lancaster any additional comments on the first reading of this uh bill again no council action will be taken this evening i just wanted
to take a moment to ask again with your name sorry my name is taylor raymond i live on the 500 block of saint joseph street um i just wanted to take a moment to ask the city clerk to please speak up
i was having trouble hearing them thank you noted any additional comments on the ordinance for first
reading good evening hi my name is lucas i live in the 400 block of west marion uh just so the public has knowledge of where to find this uh where could we look at these ordinances before
next meeting all of our proposed legislation and proposed resolutions are listed on the city website under city council if you go to the top across the top it says city government you can click the council the bottom of the page there are blocks where you can click to see proposed resolutions adopted resolutions proposed legislation those are bills and adopted legislation so bills that have been adopted by council they go back for many many meetings and agendas for all meetings once they're finalized are available in the same place as well as links to our youtube page for watching recordings of previous meetings or watching them live thank you any additional comments on the bill before us again for first reading no actions to be taken tonight hearing none we'll close that we'll move on to our next item on our agenda uh this is resolutions resolutions we begin with uh resolution number 18 2025 mr harris the resolution of the
council of the city of lancaster authorizing disposal of certain obsolete records in conformity with the retention and disposition schedule for records of pennsylvania municipalities
as previously mentioned at the start of the meeting i have made a requested report for our next meeting of council uh from the public safety um and uh although this is a routine resolution i believe it is best to table it until we have that report at our next meeting so i make a motion to table this resolution until our next meeting of council after the report requested the resolution
is not on the table yet in order to be tabled okay so we need a motion to move it forward before motion to table yeah we need a uh need a motion in a second in order to bring it to
that i will make a motion to bring it forward second and we have a second and then counselor is your motion this evening to table until which date until our next meeting of council um and
after we had the report that was requested thank you do we have a second to table second
thank you very much Mr. Harris if you would call roll the vote to table this item this evening thank you this is tabled until our next meeting our next resolution before us this evening is resolution number 19-2025 if you would please Mr. Harris
A resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster appointing special counsel for the City of Lancaster. Motion to approve. 7.
We have a motion and a second. Councillors, we spoke with this at the March 3rd meeting. This is to appoint special counsel to assist us during our negotiation process with our collective bargaining agreement through the next year. This doesn't commit us to spend any money. We heard a report from, I believe, Director Teeny Hamill on this, stating that it is an hourly rate that we would pay if we choose to or we do engage the council, but we must adopt this resolution in order to use their services. Are there any additional council comments on the resolution from the public?
Mr. Dastard.
Tony Dastard, 700 Block and New Holland Avenue. question of clarification this collective bargaining does it affect the collective of bargaining for the police union no it is not this is our asking is this apps me okay not the police okay okay thank you I just want to make the
public aware that the fees would be 365 dollars an hour or some cost to that
effect for this council or attorney can you clarify that yeah that way we can inform the public on things going on $365 hourly rate if we choose and we do use the attorney during this year yeah from taxpayer dollars because you can't do your job good evening Nicholas Rodriguez 100 block of East Walnut
Street just for clarification education could you describe some use cases where it would be necessary for either the city or the council to call on this
special counsel. Sure. These are for labor negotiations specifically. Director Campbell, if you could provide a little bit of insight on ways that we may have used special counsel for labor negotiations in the past. These aren't criminal or civil court cases. These are not courtroom. I don't want to mischaracterize them as mediation, but perhaps you could provide some insight on that.
Yeah, it's not called mediation, but it's similar to that so they would potentially help with Negotiations if we if we get to a point where we can't agree on certain things within the contracts Those would be negotiated through the attorney We they would also help us to make sure that the contract language is clear. So there's no questions about that For the AFSCME employees moving forward
So if we choose to engage them that would be the point that we do correct. Thank you any additional comments from the public on the resolution hello again uh just uh regarding the
previous comments um so they wouldn't be paid or charged until we engage with them in regards to
possible arbitrations correct okay cool any additional comments from the public on the resolution Our next resolution is a resolution number 20 20 25
Mr. Harris, if you would a resolution to the Council of the City of Lancaster approving the adoption of an amendment to the 537 official sewage facilities plan for the city of Lancaster
motion second we have a motion and a second council royal thank you council president uh this
resolution is to um expand into his capacity this specific plan amendment is for a single building containing four apartments and it's going to be constructed when a vacant lot thank you very much
council royal i also have in my notes from the previous meeting that this is a property that's outside of the city so it's sewer for non-resident account holders and i'll just remind the public that we do sewage facilities plan uh modules every time there is any sort of development and it's done to ensure that we have sewage capacity so we're passing this if we have the city has found that we have capacity for the project are there any additional uh council
comments on the resolution from the public hearing on mr. Harris and we also
have resolution 22 2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the Council of the City of
Lancaster approving the adoption of an amendment to the Act by 37 official facilities plan for the city of Lancaster motion and a second
right thank you that's president similar to the last resolution except this one is for the construction of three new single-family attached homes on six one seven Fremont Street thank you very much any comments on the resolution from the
public hearing on mr. Harris that concludes our legislative agenda this
evening we now move to our second public comment period this is open for items that were not previously on the agenda duration comments again it's three minutes for speaker and please begin with your name and your block of residence for our meeting record if you'd like to make a public comment at Please proceed to the podium at this time.
Hi, Jose Rivera, 100 block of Coral Street. This Saturday at Crystal Park, the West Crystal Volunteers will be helping and supporting Janet Diaz, and we'll be giving out reflectors for the bikes for kids. if you guys want to come down and join us we'll be at crystal park from 11 o'clock to one o'clock uh so we'll be doing that in our neighborhood make sure the kids get their reflectors because that was the reason they would stop am i right all right so we will be giving out reflectors thank you thank you good evening
cordell booth uh 400 block of locust street um here to talk about uh my friends who got assaulted by the police i know that there were a bunch of comments made tonight but those were by adults who don't know these kids those three kids i know and i go to school um when i i watched that oh my gosh i watched that post five times that night when i saw it broke my heart immediately know them like actually but i've been working on getting to know them and i've been creating a better relationship with them because of this i'm a student representative on my school board i plan to bring it up then next tuesday on our at our meeting because and honestly it's fine it's not okay because our school district hasn't said a word about it and those are our students that's not okay i'm a member of the neighborhood leadership academy at mccaskey high school i'm gonna bring it up tomorrow when we have our meeting because other students at my school need to know what is going on in my community and our community it's uh so hard for me to talk about without getting emotional because this isn't okay and it's been going on for hundreds of years and it's not okay anymore and i'm not gonna sit back like i did in 2020 and just watch it happen i'm gonna stand up and i'm gonna use my voice and i'm gonna tell you guys of Officer Hatfield and any of the other officers that were just randomly unnamed which is not okay also because they were there too they could have stopped this bullshit from happening but they didn't that's also not okay yeah I didn't write anything down
so thank you for coming here today additional comments from the public hello good evening my
name is Patrice Richards. I live on the 300 block of New Doorward. To piggyback off of the students not knowing, my husband is a teacher in the district. He did not know about this until I told him I was going to be coming here this evening. He ran into a former student of his who is now going to McCaskey who cycles. My husband is also a cyclist and he said in this interaction with a student, he was harassed by a police officer, telling him he should not be riding his bike on the street, and that he actually should be on the pavement. So I think it's really funny that we're getting on the cases about children not knowing about reflectors, lights, etc., etc., and police officers don't even know what they're enforcing. And my concern is that this child is now going to be on the pavement, and he's going to run into an officer that says, you supposed to be on the street and he's going to relay no I was told to be on the pavement and then another incident like this can occur so not only do the babies need to know about the traffic laws we as the adults need to know but also the people who are enforcing the traffic laws should know about that I literally he literally told me this as I was walking out the house and that's not okay I'm but just like for us as citizens ignorance of the law isn't enough to be exempt from it it goes for the people who are actually doing the
policing and the enforcing thank you good evening I live on the 500 block of North Street and I'm nervous to public speak and I think it always helps to call it up I believe that knowledge is power and so I want to share some context on the history of the police state the first sort of like official unofficial police state that we saw in america was in the 1700s in the carolinas they were called slave patrols slavery was central to the economy and so these slave patrols were one of the most egregious treatments of mankind in human history they were especially cruel in the ways that they captured runaway slaves and punished them for daring escape and this was the start of policing in America. After slavery was abolished during the Reconstruction era, cruelty was the policing style and police were used as a way to provide a sense of security for white communities and they aimed to keep black communities intimidated and segregated from the white population. Knowledge is power. The police state started as a way to control black and brown people in this country. that has not changed that does not change if we cannot recognize that that is the truth of American history and the police state in this country black and brown people have historically been brutalized at the hands of people in power starting in the 1700s alone just in a police state not even acknowledging the slave trade that started before that they have strictly been brutalized at the hands of people in power and they are equally neglected the benefit of the out, which is always afforded to white people. Always. We need to call this what it is. It is a clear abuse of power we've seen play out over hundreds and hundreds of years of history. Next, I want to say that every single person sitting in this room, every person is in this room because they were a kid and they survived being a kid. Black and brown kids are also kids. Those kids riding their bikes are also kids and they deserve to be kids and they deserve to grow up. They deserve to grow up in this city, in this community, with their neighbors and friends and people who care about them and look out for them and protect them and who signed an oath and took a position of power to protect them and then continue to neglect to do that. There's not a single human being in this city, on this earth, who deserves to take that right away from them and this was absolutely wrong and unacceptable. Thank you. Good evening. Good evening. My name
tale enterline i live in the manheim borough i work in the city and have basically grown up in the city i'm also one of the organizers part of the collective statement that we have put out so many thoughts and i want to point out the absence of the mayor because our demands really need to be said to her and all of y'all that a civilian review board is needed i know that there was this police working group supposedly it has transitioned in 2024 and since the three months we have been in 2025 we have seen the escalation of police violence that has been recorded that has been recorded from the violence on black and brown people and black and brown children in our community and also this happened on march 2nd all of us saw the videos on the on that uh following friday and then all these statements have came out and i won't reiterate what people have said but the statement from the police is unacceptable i am wondering i'm wondering specifically for council member arroyo and diaz as future mayor of this city what are your plans to implement to ensure trust in our community for the police to promote public safety to work with the the organizations that are reaching out to try and better like these commitments and so I will just leave it at that and to really sit with like the student who just spoke and who the black and brown children who are who are experiences as a person who also went through the police violence of the city from 2020 and now we're about to put kids through the system because of the charges they're putting out that again should just be a fine and it had to go through that trauma is unacceptable it's trauma and it's reiteration of that power that they are trying to put on the black and brown people and the children and it's not okay and it's unacceptable thank you Darlene Burden Street I just want to
make some clarity we're talking about having a review board the city of Lancaster has never had an independent police review board or a community review board we keep talking about reinstating it there was not one the review board needs to have some teeth to it a lot of this was brought up when we used to have public safety when we used to have public safety meetings and council would have a day that they met and you would get to come in and discuss public safety issues and the other different departments so maybe before a lot of your time but this was addressed then and I just want to make that clear when we're asking for a review board we're asking for something that has teeth not what we've had but something new and we're asking council to act on it now we don't want to wait till we get a new mayor we don't want to wait till we get four new councilmen this is something or council women this is something that we can do right now and i think you have heard from the public and we're asking council to take action on this and go ahead and let's have this independent review board thank you
pastor kevin brown of kingdom life international assembly 900 east king street i did not come prepared to speak tonight but it is obvious that there's tension in the community about this incident and about the ongoing issues with the police department and the public. It has reached a situation where now the youth are at risk because there is not a proper relationship between law enforcement and the community. My question is, since we have already, and I know that I've been a part of conversations about having a community review board years ago, and there was no real attention given to it, I am saddened that the mayor and the chief of police is not here tonight. the mayor and the chief of police should be answering to the behaviors of the officers that committed these atrocities with the community and I would like to suggest that after a proper investigation is initiated and officer hatfield and the others are removed from their position so that there is no further um controversy in that regard about whether a police officer who has already committed an atrocity towards the community is still allowed to execute policing that the public safety committee would possibly do a town hall meeting and with the mayor and the police chief being there to hear from the community what should be needed to rectify this situation as well as ongoing efforts to try to bring some healing to this situation with the disparities between the police or law enforcement and the
community thank you good evening thanks so much for hearing our comments tonight my name is Samantha Swigert I'm on the 100 block of North Ann Street I had not seen the police's response to the police response until this evening when I I looked it up, and I just wanted to call attention to something that caught my eye. It reads, the individuals involved in the incident have had several interactions with the police bureau for trespassing in garages, pulling fire alarms, blocking travel lanes, riding near pedestrians, and causing traffic issues, putting others and themselves in danger. And I just want to point out that that sounds like any given day at the high school, middle school boys and girls club the mix in the hallways like these are kids um they they sound like they're being kids it sounds like a prefrontal cortex that isn't fully formed and won't be for another 10 years if we're talking about the individuals that were involved in the march second incident um and i bring this recent police incident of brutality up and i bring this up because i have a background in working with youth i have friends who work with youth i have friends who are teachers and staff at schools many of whom make far less than our police force do and they would never be allowed to treat a child in this way kids get annoying they do silly things and then they get sent to detention and we we do some repair work that's not what happened here if if a professional that works with youth ever acted in this way with a youth they would be barred for work from working with youth moving forward and it would follow them it would follow them throughout their entire professional career thereafter so if we're looking at our teachers and our youth development professionals and we demand that level of accountability with folks who work with youth on a daily basis and deal with these kinds of incidents every day then I think we need to hold the same level of accountability for the folks that our taxpaying dollars
go toward thank you hello Matt Hoyer I live on the 600 block of West Chestnut before I begin I would like to echo the sentiments that have been expressed tonight but I'm here today to ask that the city re-examine the pedestrian safety of the intersection of College Avenue Pearl Street and Columbia's Columbia Avenue current situation the intersections focused around Columbia with Pearl and College being offsets the traffic signals are in order Columbia Pearl College and the pedestrian crossings illuminate with the green light this is normal for many intersections but I believe that this is a bad idea for this particular one this is because drivers making left turns out of Pearl and College tend to charge through the intersection without paying attention to the crosswalks and unless someone's already in the middle of the street then they may not get a chance to cross until all the red light runners have gone through and if you don't think there's red light runners then you have not been a pedestrian this is something that I've both seen and experienced many times personally including for example last Friday around 2 30 p.m. where I I watched a jogger not able to cross the intersection after until all 20 cars had gone through I believe that fixing this issue is especially important because of two nearby bus stops at Columbia and Pearl and Columbia and Ruby which serve the Millersville and Columbia bus routes in fact this is the main reason why I personally tend to cross Columbia at this point I understand that there's only so much that the city can do due to the wonky nature of the built environment however I'd still like to see the city do something in regards to pedestrian safety to make pedestrians feel safer crossing this intersection in accordance with its own safe streets plan my suggestion is to light the pedestrian signals at college at pearl and college a few seconds before the green light much like the city does with its downtown area in order to give pedestrians a chance to get into the intersection so that the drivers can actually see them and then maybe hesitate frankly I'm I don't know the actual numbers but frankly I'm I'd be surprised that more people haven't been hit injured killed at this intersection thank you for your time thank you
Nicholas Rodriguez 100 block of East Walnut I've lived in Lancaster since I I was about three, I went to McCaskey. I don't have experience working with children, but I've experienced as a child a few years ago. I'm Puerto Rican, as you can see, visibly brown. And growing up, I was always told, don't call the police on someone you're not willing to see dead. And for good reason, because once you make that call, that power is out of your hands And I've seen a lot of situations where it would be helpful to have a third party to, you know, at least separate the people involved, you know, instances of domestic violence, things of that nature. When there's that potential of this, do I want to see this person permanently punished? Do I want to see this person's life ruined or do I just need them to stop what they're doing now? When you're given that choice, a lot of people are going to understandably choose not to engage the police, which then makes them feel less unsafe because your only other option is try to argue with this person or a nuclear weapon, you're gonna try to stick it out even though you will continue to be in danger. And to a lot of people, I think it's honestly unfair for the chief of police and the mayor to not be here to saddle all of our public comments with you all. You know, you have an important job, but it's limited in scope. The specific things you can do aren't as... the mayor and the chief can change things immediately. There's only so much you all can do so thank you for hearing us all out. Thank you.
Tony D'Astra, 700 block New Holland Avenue. Before I forget I want to actually agree with Mr. Matt Boyer back there that there should be a study done on that intersection and if a study is done I'd encourage you to look into evaluating all-way stops or all-way crossings where everything's a pedestrian crossing all at once I think they're great but I digress because that's not why we're here tonight or at least not why I came tonight I agree with the members of the public that are upset that the mayor is not here tonight as well as the chief of police ultimately like I don't wanna give too much flack here but like ultimately the mayor is the conductor of the concert that is police and chief of police is first violin you guys are like the rhythm section like you're important you have the ability to push this concert forward or bring it back but that being said it is a concert and this issue of policing should become increasingly important for our local communities as we are concerned with federal destabilization you know ultimately a people needs to be in concert with its people who have force because we are living in an era where we don't know who's necessarily fighting for our rights anymore we want to know that our police are doing that you know I understand where everybody's coming with we need to fire officer Hatfield I believe it is but we also have the problem of there's a police union there are procedures for terminating officers and those sometimes Wow come in conflict with what we're looking to see as a community at a certain point in time. So the investigations need to continue but it doesn't remove the fact that right now there's clearly a disconnect between the public and policing and I also agree with the public sentiments that we really need to establish the citizen review board. In the 21st century we don't get the opportunity to do these internal investigations where the evidence is in the police headquarters and it's reviewed or taken to a third party we are living in an era where everyone is an investigator everyone's a reporter everyone has a camera so we really should aim to have a more cohesive process for how we can work through these issues because ultimately we need a good police force we need to know who's on our side this is a complicated matter but we've we have unfortunately been through this use of force concern before we need to break this cycle thank you hello Lucas again
from 400 west marion um based on all these comments uh today i believe we are all under the impression that in a way we are under fire from the police um that being said there is a disturbing trend within this country of the gradual and continual militarization of police we cannot be expected to be protected by a force who treats us as a threat and as prey and that is how a lot of these um people are being trained either they're having retreats and going on these specific uh being taught by tutors who teach these officers to treat us as constant threats when we do have a citizen review board not if when we have a citizen review board i believe it's a necessity that we also take a good look at how we are training our officers and if these individuals are coming from the military that they are receiving the proper therapy and trauma care that they need to come back from an active combat zone into civilian life. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, good. I don't really talk in the microphones all day so I'm going to try and make this as streamlined as possible.
If you could just begin with your name and block of residence.
Yep. My name is Roe Potter. i'm on the 600 block of south franklin street i wasn't really sure how that worked until i got up here i come here tonight not fully educated on what was going on with the car uh the cops stopping that uh the two young individuals earlier in the week and it took my partner bringing it to my attention for me to get a reaction out of it and this is important to me because i'm sweaty stinky smelly from spending all day educating and working with kids for the YWCA I sit I see a few of my YW friends around here somewhere I can't pinpoint you but I see you I spend all day working with these kids and telling them to look up to the people that are making our laws and running our country and I gotta tell them the President of the United States or a government official isn't exactly let's go on change the foot end of our society and in fact I think everyone should look around at who's actually here tonight and who left midway to give their comments in the beginning this is actually who's listening who's affected and who is going to make the change they can listen but it's like my friend said before they are the people stopping the main comments from getting to the top so what we say actually matters but what we do and what we rally is actually way more important than me getting up here and saying this on a microphone so please everyone look at each other and get a name get a phone number get Instagram or whatever talk organize we don't have to put up with this
Jessica Lopez Lancaster resident I promise I'm not coming back to yellow one let me say that yes there are unions and you still without union issues put that man on the desk don't let him out his office you don't want to fire him he's hiding behind the Union put him in the office do not give him a gun do not allow him to run around our city no union can stop you from doing that and yes I get it y'all are not the key element in this movement but you are here to uphold the one person who is supposed to uphold the chief so yes this is on use and I get it some of y'all like her y'all are not here to protect her feelings you are here to protect us and then in that protection I ask what does the safety working committee do is it to prevent and protect and bring safety measures before the issue or is it to allow an issue to bust out and then be like oh come to Crystal Park we'll give you free reflectors you're too late janet it was your job as the safety committee to have this education put out before those panhandling notices came out because y'all managed to do that real quickly i'm disgusted beyond disgusted we're not tired of the white representative we're not tired of the black representative we're tired of the complacent representative that think they're going to come in here lean back be comfortable and capitalize off of us that's what we're tired of janet so you could quote me on that and to the guy that just came up here i want you to know that those people that left they work tirelessly day in and day out to clean this city up not every one of them but understand that we don't get paid for all our hours heck I just started working for the bail fund I've been doing this I've been coming to see y'all for how many years now I just started getting paid for this and yes I reiterate that it is up to the city to educate these children and it is up now to our community to give them those reflectors we don't need our kids around you gaslighting like that good evening
Diane Desmond I live off Route 30 stones throw away from the state police so I wanted to in the interest of keeping the council accountable there was a promise during the first round of public comments that you would recall the names of the people who were not first there and then just was hoping that you could
do that good evening my name is so beta Rosa former Lancaster City resident now I live in Lancaster Township and I also yes so beta Rosa formerly Lancaster City resident current Lancaster Township resident also a co-founder of the Lancaster changemakers collective I've heard a lot of people talk about that there's not a proper relationship between the police and the community but there is a presence there is a presence in the schools the school district pays for school resource officers what are they doing if not educating the students on how they can ride bicycles in their own community that is very confusing to me also the police do their rounds at least in the southeast when I visit my grandparents when I visit my friends they are doing their rounds their presence is known those SUVs you can see them coming but they are not talking to the people that live in those communities also the police made this statement on March 10th this incident happened on March 2nd so without public outrage were they not going to address it was nothing gonna happen was no investigation gonna happen are we just allowed to brutalize people and they had the body camera footage who's analyzing that somebody saw that footage other officers saw Hatfield me somebody is there no accountability within that organization and they have a union to protect them to keep brutalizing people that's insane before my job that I get paid for I go into the Youth Intervention Center three times a month to talk about healthy relationships with the youth three times a month I see children in orange sweaters in gray sweatpants with no shoes on in a room for an hour they get padded before they come in they get padded down before they leave they are up for 12 hours a day and when they're not in classes or in programming they're in a cell these are children that are incarcerated they have to earn extra privileges like nice soap and an extra phone call so if these if we don't drop the charges if you're not behind dropping the charges for this for these youth they will become incarcerated they will become part of a dehumanizing system and then what does that say are we just saying that they're not worth anything because they're black and brown and because they dare to ride a bike outside in their own community
that's all I have to say typically we we have a one three minutes but it's your first meeting and I'm sure being here so all right honestly I wanted a Cordell
booth 400 block Lucas I just said what that lady said before me I forgot her name i'm sorry uh she's right what the hell are the school resource officers doing at my school listen i respect them i talk to them i try to communicate with them i mean for when i see them they don't do anything they sit in the hallways and they watch and wait for probably students to get into a fight that's not okay and i want them to start teaching students that are uneducated about what they can about laws because it's not okay and i want my friends to be safe in my community my friends invited me to play basketball tonight at the park and i told them no because i wanted to be here because this was a little bit more important than playing basketball but also because i remember being in middle school and i was at that park and there were two of my of two other people on the other side of the court getting absolutely harassed by officers asking them questions and harassing them and i didn't say a word because i was scared i'm not scared anymore i mean miss baker you heard you said it i'm trying to make my mom proud right now and every single day that i go out and i represent her and my dad i want to make i want to make them proud man and every day that i see kids that are going through this absolute bs i can't take it anymore and i'm not just going to like stand by and let it happen and i'm going and i really do want the mayor to be here and i want the chief of police to be here because they need to hear me and all of these other people talk about what they should do because again as i've repeatedly had to say it's not okay it's not when i leave next year when i go off to college whichever one of you two is the mayor whichever one which i will be voting in because i'll be 18. but whichever one you use the mayor how are you going to protect my friends that are still at mccaskey that are still in the middle schools that are still at these programs that i summer camp council at for months trying to teach kids about the stuff that's happening in this messed up world and how they can stay safe and be and still be together and have community and feel community this all these people i don't know any of these people except for a few i've never honest i don't know if i'm ever going to see them again right everybody here is different everybody here is a different color different shade different hair we all deserve the same respect and the last thing i'm going to say about the police is that thank god i'm not in that i was never in that situation however i know i have a permit i have a driving permit when i'm driving on the roads whenever i see police not only now sorry mom not only is my mom scared sometimes we drive past the lease i have severe anxiety that's diagnosed by a doctor i have anxiety when i drive by the police i can't i shouldn't be scared they're there to protect me i live in this city my parents pay their my parents pay their salaries i deserve to be safe in this city
along with everybody else all right that's all i got an opportunity as i mentioned before for the folks that might have been on the list for the first public comment period so i'm going to say names i may butcher them but if any of these folks are here please you can come forward at this time uh alia mocos grace musser um megan keller uh amanda reitz and ann torres and iris martinez i believe were the folks that were not here if i have my notes correct so if any of them are here please come forward um you're not one of those people that's fine i don't see any of them right now, they can walk forward with time, but please go ahead. Thank you. Thank you, Council.
I'm sorry. I'm Ann Torres. Oh, you did.
Okay. Thank you very much. I just, my notes were a little jumbled from earlier. Thank you.
Good evening. Thank you. Hi. Good evening. Evelyn Morales, 900 block of Walbank Street. I did not come here prepared to speak tonight, and just so you're aware, who's in the room? We have a group of social work students here from Millersville, and so we are here to see how our government is functioning at a local level, and your response to community concerns so please be aware that this is the future you're sending out that being said I'm a city resident I have four kids in the district and I just want to reiterate that yes you know we should be teaching our kids how to ride a bike it's so much information think about how long it took you to try to pass a permit a permit to get your driver's license that is a lot that you're asking a 10 year old to retain and on top of that we're changing the streets to accommodate these bike lanes and not no two streets are the same so you're asking them to learn all this in real time when adults can't so please when as you're continuing to expand these bike lanes take that into consideration take into consideration your audience have more education and in the schools and reach people where they are we talk about different ways to reach people like we're going to have a zoom meeting we're going to have something in person we're going to have something that's walkable so please keep that in mind thank you any additional
comments for this is here okay this is just for uh suzy gomez 100 block of north reservoir street this is just for clarity i am about to be 50 years old in nine months i have a 32 year old and a 27-year-old. I literally had to take to address an officer to remove the handcuffs off of my son because he pulled him out of the back seat of a vehicle, okay? And he immediately, well, he just put him on the floor as if they are just dogs, okay? It is disgusting. I've been in this city since 1992. My daughter graduated from Lancaster Mennonite. She's 32, and my son graduated from McCaskey. He's 27. I am not a spring chick, okay? I was under the administration with Ray D'Agostino, who is county commissioner, who was my boss, and I had dealings with a lot of people in the city. I've done my due diligence. I've done my community work, and I've damn sure done my homework okay and what I see is unexplainable it's beyond words that's why a lot of times I stutter because it's unbelievable how much red tape and how much you're getting away with there are people that need housing there are issues in our city that need to be attended and it is not a rocket science because one plus one equals two to handle your responsibilities and address your oath that you declared to serve the people not the administration it is shameful to not see the mayor here or the police officer but it's even more shameful how i can actually witness being an ex-housing development coordinator how much damage this administration and other people in power has done not only to our neighborhoods I can't even drive in the southeast because I got to keep dodging holes because you guys don't even want to pave the streets with taxpayer dollar but you got all these infrastructures you got all these plans for Lancaster City and none of them can actually I can't even tell my five grandbabies that they have a future here because they might not even afford to rent let alone it is shameful especially for you motherless people that don't have a child and are making decisions based on taxpayer dollar you should be ashamed of yourself you should do your job and go out into the streets and actually get to know the community. Meet with people that are paying your tax that are paying your salary.
Are there any further comments for the second
period? Taylor Raymond again 500 block of St. Joseph Street. Is it normal for the mayor and the chief of police to be at these meetings? Is this an unusual circumstance that they aren't here?
The chief of police normally doesn't attend regular meetings unless there's a report that's been requested like we were talking about earlier. The mayor typically does attend these meetings. She has a prior commitment and was not able to be here and that's as much as I can say. I don't have a way to compel the mayor to attend, but typically yes.
Okay, thank you.
Hi, sorry I didn't have, oh Leah Strickler and I'm on North Charlotte Street. I didn't have anything prepared today but I wanted to speak on um the comments that people made about education and educating these kids and resources and that sort of thing that's great but at the end of the day what should be happening is we should be holding these police officers accountable it doesn't matter if these kids don't know the laws they they aren't in school for learning bike laws they're in school these these police officers are are the ones that need to be held accountable not these kids not their parents not the community it's the police brutality that's the issue thank
you Alessandra McAleely 100 block south and straight up just have a quick question is anybody filing assault charges against these officers I have no
knowledge of any charges that are wrong I don't know one way or the other has he even been put on administrative leave i do not know the answer to that question how do we get the answers i suspect that there will be additional communications coming out from the police bureau in the coming days it's just on information that i have at this time thank you
i personally went down and filed a complaint with the police i put it on facebook
are there any additional public comments for this period Miss Rosa, you have already gone, so I'll give you just a moment if you have additional
comments. Thank you. It was just a quick question. What's the best way to reach out to counselors to give our grievances and to work with y'all to get to see what we, the change that we want done? Obviously people can just come and yell at you, but like what's the most productive way to get stuff done?
You're welcome to do that, but each of us have a contact information on the same city website that I was referencing earlier about finding legislation, and I'm not sure if you're here for that part, under the City of Lancaster. It's also just our first initial and last name
at cityoflancaster.gov. And do you have any information about the social workers that work within the police department and if they were involved in this incident? I have no information
about whether they were a part of this incident or not. I've seen nothing to indicate that they were, but I don't know for sure. Thank you. Are there additional comments for this hearing? Hearing none, we'll close the public comment period this evening and I want to thank everyone for your participation. The next item on the agenda would have been a report of a mayor, but I don't have one in part this time. The next item is a report of the president of council. I did give a statement earlier this evening, so I won't reiterate that, but I will say that as a childless person, I am also a city resident. i work with children every day as the director of programs for a non-profit in the city that serves youth and i take deep offense that i'm not qualified to make good decisions for our residents simply because i've chosen not to have a child and that's nobody's business mr gomez thank you you've given your comment tonight and i take offense to that statement i would just like to say that i'd like to believe that i make good decisions and if you don't believe that i make good decisions please don't say that i do so because i don't have a chance
because i do want to address the the very full room that we have here tonight
and i want to say thank you all for coming exercising your first amendment right to
petition to assemble and to protest and it's your right to yell at us and we have to listen so that's that's part of the job i really don't have a lot to say i don't want to say all that much about the incident because all i'm going to say is that there needs to be a thorough a thorough investigation of the events because i was disturbed by what i saw as a citizen and as a step out and i was an auditor so i looked at details um when i was in that role i looked at documentation it has to be thorough there cannot be holes um i don't see how we get there without the body uh camera footage coming out personally we have a lot of uh a lot of um between this resolution and i've taken detailed notes on all the comments that came here tonight we have a lot to consider um when we legislate there are details there there are you know state laws there are federal laws that govern and limit us in some capacity but all of these ideas i plan to research them i plan to pursue them to the extent that we can alongside my colleagues so again i'm not going to say anything more but i think council has work to do and the police force absolutely has work to do in engaging the community and earning their trust back yes
I would like to say that it was very disturbing watching the video and just like Amanda says
just because I don't have children it doesn't mean I don't understand. I lost I lost a nephew who I was going to adopt at the age of 17 because he had cancer and he was bullied because he was So I also understand that. I have worked with the police. I have worked very hard to find ways to make it better. But there is also the executive, which is the mayor, that also has to make decisions on any policy that's going to come out. And it also goes to a solicitor. It's not something that is very easily done. but I just want to say thank you for coming because it does show that you do
care and I just want to thank everybody who came out and spoke tonight and I was disturbed by the videos as well and you know some of the comments that are made today what is the power of counsel in these matters I have one of the powers council is reports requested for council and that's why i have requested a report on what the use of force policy is and what the review process will look like and i look forward to seeing that report and just one last comment um you know we appreciate everybody who comes out and uses their political advocacy to speak at these meetings uh but i just want to um you know i'm very disturbed by comments especially during about women's history you know calling out elected officials for not having children i mean we have to have a quorum in these chambers i understand people are very passionate about these issues uh but you know we have people who are working very hard and whether we have children or not i mean it's just unacceptable to be talking about that um and i hope that we could all learn from that and you know treat each other with respect but you know these are very distinguished chambers and i take this very seriously so these comments about people being childless especially in a month that we're celebrating women's history is unacceptable
thank you council president uh just wanted to address the crowd that's here this evening um first thank you for coming this evening to share your thoughts your concerns your ideas um you know as my colleagues have mentioned you know part of the process whenever we're trying to find solutions is coming together uh and even if the conversations are uncomfortable they're very very much important and uh it's very um humbling to see the community come together to to to drive some of these solutions i i saw the video um it was brought to my attention by a friend of mine that i was not aware of it before um and first i saw you know i saw that video as myself but god knows that i've done worse things on my bike as a teenager um and then i saw it as As a father, we set a goal for my son to learn how to ride his bike this summer. So first and foremost, before being elected official, counselor, whatever, that's the lens that I'm seeing that video through. And I expect any city employee to have compassion, empathy, and accountability for our residents. And you can do all of those at the same time in a respectful, compassionate manner. And I believe and I'm optimistic in the leadership in this city, including my council colleagues to come up with a solution that will uh that will create a culture where um as mr booth said uh make everyone feel safe and that is the priority of everyone that works for the city of lancaster um so thank you all for coming tonight and uh we hear you thank
you council please thank you madam president i thank you all for coming and uh i already address to the video on my platform but i understand the concern raised by the community regarding the video it was disturbing and it caused the pain and concerns every resident of lancaster this year to feel saved and respected and it is important that all interactions between law enforcement and city residents are handled with professionalism and respect i believe that the department should conduct an independent investigation and take up real actions because the moments like this we cannot afford to let this uh unchecked thank you for coming
i'm sorry sir yes since council members you've seen the decision yes make sure this office at least put on administrative fees for the next 40, 24 years.
We don't have additional comments from the public
at this period, but I appreciate your question. The answer is that, yes, I know that I will personally be in contact with the mayor tomorrow, very first thing in the morning, on a calendar. And I believe that the comments from members of council affirm our commitment to making sure that there is a resolution to this, and that it is expeditious, whatever that resolution may be. So thank you. We're at the end of our agenda for this evening. So at this time, I'll hear a motion to adjourn.
Motion to adjourn. Second.
We need a motion and a second. All in favor?
Aye. Aye.
We are adjourned. Thank you.
It's so crazy to see you all.